Guide to the Amadeus Grabau papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Amadeus Grabau Papers,
1909-1940
Grabau, Amadeus W. (Amadeus William), 1870-1946.
5 linear ft. (ca. 20 items in 10 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5419398
Biographical Note
Amadeus William Grabau, 1870-1946, American geologist and paleontologist. Grabau taught at MIT (1892-1897), Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (1899-1901), and Columbia University (1901-1919). He then went to China, were he was chief paleontologist for the Chinese Geological Survey and professor at Peking National University. Grabau was known for his work on world stratigraphic deposits and the deciphering of Earth history.
Scope and Content
Manuscripts, galley proofs, and books by Amadeus Grabau. The manuscripts drafts are autograph and typed, occasionally accompanied by notes, correspondence, and related materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 1 series:
Series I: Contents List
Subjects
Geology.; Paleontology.; Geology, Stratigraphic.; Fossils.; Invertebrates.; Geologist.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
- Series I: Contents List
  - Galley proof of "Textbook of Geology", ca. 1920 (Box 1)
  - Autograph and typed manuscript drafts of "Principles of Stratigraphy (Part I)", ca. 1913 (Box 2)
  - Autograph and typed manuscript drafts of "Principles of Stratigraphy (Part I)" Also includes unidentified typed manuscript. ca. 1913 (Box 3)
  - Bound galley proofs and published version of "Principles of Stratigraphy", 1913 (Box 4)
  - Typed manuscript of "Geology of Non-Metallic Mineral Deposits Other Than Silicates Vol. II The Geological Succession of Salt Deposits", 1922 (Box 5)
  - Autograph manuscript of "Geology of Non-Metallic Mineral Deposits Other Than Silicates Vol. II The Geological Succession of Salt Deposits", pp. 511-1400, ca. 1922 (Box 6)
  - Autograph manuscript of "Geology of Non-Metallic Mineral Deposits Other Than Silicates Vol. II The Geological Succession of Salt Deposits", pp. 1401-1688. Also includes article on the Sinian System and "A Memoir on the Devonic Formation of Michigan", ca. 1922-1924 (Box 7)
  - Bound autograph manuscripts of "Geology of Non-Metallic Mineral Deposits Other Than Silicates Vol. II The Geological Succession of Salt Deposits", Chapters XV-XXXV, ca. 1922 (Box 8)
  - Bound copies of North American Index Fossils: Invertebrates, Volumes I and III, by Grabau and Hervey Woodburn Shimer. The books are inscribed by Grabau to his research assistant Mary Welleck [Garretson], 1909-1910 (Box 9)
  - Bound copies of The Rhythms of the Ages and Palaeozoic Formations in the Light of the Pulsations Theory, Volumes II-IV. These books were published in China and are inscribed by Grabau to his research assistant Alice Woodland Graham, 1936-1940 (Box 10)